<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mathsci.co</title>
    <description>mathsci.co delivers and presents common math and science homework problems for you to prepare for your exams.</description>
    <link>http://mathsci.co//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://mathsci.co//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 15:14:22 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2015 15:14:22 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry I - U5LM3B</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;u5lm3b-ws-limiting-reagent--percent-yield&quot;&gt;U5LM3B-WS Limiting Reagent &amp;amp; Percent Yield&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I. Methanol, CH3OH, is used as a fuel. Recall that combustion reactions produce carbon dioxide and water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Write a balanced chemical equation for the combustion reaction.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2CH3OH + 3O2 → 2CO2 + 4H2O&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) How many moles of carbon dioxide are produced in each of the following cases?&lt;br /&gt;
Include calculations quantifying the number of moles left over for any excess reactants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 2 mols of CH3OH react with 3 mols of O2.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;2 mol CH3OH x 2 mol CO2 / 2 mol CH3OH =&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2 mol CO2 max&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;3molO2 x 2molCO2 / 3 mol O2 = 2 mol CO2 max&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;These reagents are in stoichiometric equivalence, so both reagents react completely.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;0 moles of excess reagent&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) 2 mols of CH3OH react with 2 mols of O2&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;2 mol CH3OH x 2 mol CO2 / 2 mol CH3OH = 2 mol CO2 max&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;2 mol O2 x 2 mol CO2 / 3 mol O2 =&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1.33 mol CO2 max&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;2 mol O2 x 2 mol CH3OH / 3 mol O2 = 1.33 mol CH3OH used&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
CH3OH excess reagent&lt;br /&gt;
O2 limiting reagent&lt;br /&gt;
2-1.33 = &lt;strong&gt;0.67 moles excess methanol&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;c) 3 mols of CH3OH react with 3 mols of O2&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Perform hypothetical maximum calculations as above. Another way of determining the limiting reagent is to say…” 3 moles of methanol would require 4.5 moles of oxygen. We only have 3 moles of O2, so oxygen must be limiting.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;3 mol CH3OH x 3 mol O2 / 2 mol CH3OH = 4.5 mol O2 required&lt;/em&gt; … O2 is limiting&lt;br /&gt;
All of the oxygen will react…&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;3molO2 x 2molCO2 / 3 mol O2 =&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;2 mol CO2 produced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;3 mol O2 x 2 mol CH3OH / 3 mol O2 = 2 mol CH3OH used;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1 mole of excess methanol&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;d) 88 g of CH3OH react with 88 g of O2&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;These problems require you to convert grams using the molar mass before performing steps above. Note: methanol and oxygen have different molecular formulas but happen to have similar molar masses.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;88 g CH3OH x 1 mol CH3OH / 32 g CH3OH x 2 mol CO2 / 2 mol CH3OH = 2.75 mol CO2 max&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;CH3OH excess reagent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;88 g O2 x 1 mol O2 / 32 g O2 x 2molCO2 / 3 mol O2 =&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;1.83 mol CO2 max&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;O2 limiting reagent&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;1.83 mol CO2 x 2 mol CH3OH / 2 mol CO2 = 1.83 mol CH3OH used&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;88 g CH3OH x 1 mol CH3OH / 32 g CH3OH = 2.75 mol CH3OH available – 1.83 mol used =&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;0.92 mol excess CH3OH&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;e) 15 g of CH3OH react with 12 g of O2&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;15g CH3OH x 1 mol / 32 g = 0.47 mol CH3OH available … x(3mol O2 / 2mol CH3OH) = 0.71 mol O2 required&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;12g O2 x 1 mol / 32 g = only 0.375 mol O2 available…. So O2 is limiting.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;All of the oxygen will react… 0.375 mol O2 x 2 mol CO2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;0.375 mol O2 x 2 mol CH3OH / 3 mol O2 =&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;0.25 mol CO2 produced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;= 0.25 mol CH3OH used; (0.47–0.25) =&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;0.22 mole excess methanol&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;f) 25 g of CH3OH react with 35 g of O2&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;0.78 mol CH3OH available&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;1.17 mol O2 required&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;1.09 mol O2 available&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;0.73 mol CO2 produced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;0.05 mole excess methanol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;II. Propane is by-product of natural gas processing and petroleum refining. It is commonly used as a fuel for engines, oxy-gas torches, barbecues, portable stoves, and residential central heating.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;C3H8 +5O2 → 3CO2 +4H2O&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Note: C3H8 and CO2 have different molecular formulas but happen to have similar molar masses.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) What mass of CO2 is produced when 6.5 g of propane is reacted with 14.2 g of O2?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;11.7 g CO2 produced (theoretical yield)&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b) The actual yield of the reaction described above is 8.0 g of carbon dioxide. What is the percent yield?&lt;br /&gt;
Percent yield is how much you got out of how much you could theoretically get… 8.0 g CO2 / 11.7 g CO2 x 100% = &lt;strong&gt;68 % yield&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;III. Nitrogen dioxide reacts with hydrogen to produce nitrogen and water. When 125g of nitrogen dioxide are allowed to react with excess hydrogen, the percent yield is 35%. How many grams of each product are actually formed during this process?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;2 NO2 + 4 H2 → N2 + 4 H2O&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;13.3 g N2 produced&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;34.3 g H2O produced&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mathsci.co//chemistry/U5LM3B/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mathsci.co//chemistry/U5LM3B/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry I - LM 22</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-module-22--molecular-orbital-theory--guided-reading-activity&quot;&gt;LEARNING MODULE 22 – Molecular Orbital Theory – Guided Reading Activity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can molecular orbital calculations tell us about molecules?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MO calculations can predict geometries: giving the relative positions of atoms within the molecule such that you can determine bond lengths, bond strengths, and bond angles&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mathematically the MO quantum mechanical calculations give:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A set of orbitals and energies in which the electrons of all the atoms within the molecule can be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the lowest energy molecular orbitals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quantum mechanical calculations are repeated moving the atoms with various bond lengths, strengths and angles until the minimum energy is achieved. This set of lowest energy molecular orbitals is then the suggested set for the molecule. The electrons are then filled form lowest to highest energy. From there, the bond order and magnetism can be predicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the potential energy diagram under the Molecular Geometry tab. The diagram is for diatomic molecular hydrogen. State here the labels for the x and y-axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The y-axis is the potential energy of the system. The minimum of the curve is the minimum potential energy of the system. The x-axis is the inter-nuclear distance between the two atoms. The x value that corresponds with the y-min is the optimum inter-nuclear distance and is considered to be the bond length.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Referring to the MO and Hydrogen Molecule tab. Sketch the MO diagram here. Label the atomic orbitals, the bonding MO and the anti-bonding MO. Explain why you see 4 arrows in this diagram and the significance of each arrow. State the origin of the bonding MO versus the anti-bonding MO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MO1 is the bonding orbital.&lt;br /&gt;
MO2 is and anti-bonding orbital.&lt;br /&gt;
1 arrow is the 1s electron for one atom of H (labeled A in this diagram), the other is the electron originating from the other H (labeled B in this diagram). Then, the 2 arrows in the bonding MO originate from the atoms (A&amp;amp;B). The Bonding MOs arise mathematically from the constructive addition of the atomic wave functions while the Anti- Bonding MOs arise from the destructive addition of the atomic wave functions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bonding orbitals have &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;lower&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; energy than the atomic orbitals from which they are formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anti-Bonding orbitals have &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; energy than the atomic orbitals from which they are formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of MO theory, a sigma bond is a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;end to end or head to head&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; overlap of atomic orbitals showing where there is a high probability of finding electrons between atoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anti-bonding orbitals are also &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;end to end or head to head&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; overlap, but in this case the overlap is destructive, so there is no probability of finding the electrons in the place directly between the atoms because the overlap results in a &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;node&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bond order predicts the number of bonds that should be found in a molecule based on the calculated molecular orbitals and the total number of electrons in the molecule. Write the equation for calculating bond order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;BO = 1⁄2(# Bonding electrons - # Anti-bonding electrons)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the MO energy diagrams given for common diatomics, calculate the bond order for B2. What does this value tell you about the stability of that particular diatomic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case B has 5 electrons. So, if you fill in the 10 electrons that exist in this diatomic from lowest to highest on the MO Energy level diagram you end up with 6 bonding electrons and 4 anti-bonding electrons. So, the BO = 1⁄2(6-2) = 1. So you predict that this diatomic could form with a single bond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paramagnetic compounds (and atoms) are &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;attracted to&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;/from magnetic fields, while diamagnetic compounds (and atoms) are &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;repelled&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; to/&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; magnetic fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Label and define HOMO and LUMO on the following diagram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The HOMO is the σ2p. The LUMO is the π2p*. HOMO stands for Highest Occupied Molecular Orbital and LUMO stands for Lowest Unoccupied Molecular Orbital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mathsci.co//chemistry/lm-22/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mathsci.co//chemistry/lm-22/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry I - Chap 9 Review</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-9-bonding-and-molecular-structure-orbital-hybridization-and-molecular-orbitals&quot;&gt;CHAPTER 9: Bonding and Molecular Structure: Orbital Hybridization and Molecular Orbitals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;orbitals-and-theories-of-chemical-bonding&quot;&gt;9.1 Orbitals and Theories of Chemical Bonding&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which one of the statements concerning valence bond (VB) and molecular orbital (MO) bond theories is correct?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) MO theory predicts that electrons are localized between pairs of atoms.&lt;br /&gt;
b) In VB theory, bonding electrons are delocalized over the molecule.&lt;br /&gt;
c) MO theory accurately describes bonding in O2 and NO, VB theory does not.&lt;br /&gt;
d) VB theory can describe molecular bonding in excited states.&lt;br /&gt;
e) MO theory is used to accurately predict the colors of compounds.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;valence-bond-theory&quot;&gt;9.2 Valence Bond Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following statements is/are CORRECT?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The overlap between an s orbital and a p orbital is called a pi-bond.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The overlap of two s orbitals in H2 is called a sigma bond.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HF is formed from the overlap of a hydrogen 1s orbital with a fluorine 2s orbital.   &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1 only&lt;br /&gt;
b) 2 only&lt;br /&gt;
c) 3 only&lt;br /&gt;
d) 2 and 3&lt;br /&gt;
e) 1, 2, and 3  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following statements concerning hybrid orbitals is/are CORRECT?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of hybrid orbitals equals the number of atomic orbitals that are used to create the hybrids.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When atomic orbitals are hybridized, the s orbital and at least one p orbital are always hybridized.  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To create octahedral structures, two d orbitals must be hybridized along with the s and all three p orbitals.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1 only&lt;br /&gt;
b) 2 only&lt;br /&gt;
c) 3 only&lt;br /&gt;
d) 2 and 3&lt;br /&gt;
e) 1, 2, and 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: e&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many sigma (σ) bonds and pi (π) bonds are in ethene, C2H4?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) four σ, one π&lt;br /&gt;
b) four σ, two π&lt;br /&gt;
c) five σ, one π&lt;br /&gt;
d) five σ, two π&lt;br /&gt;
e) six σ, zero π  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many sigma (σ) bonds and pi (π) bonds are in carbon monoxide?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) three σ, zero π&lt;br /&gt;
b) two σ, one π&lt;br /&gt;
c) two σ, two π&lt;br /&gt;
d) one σ, two π&lt;br /&gt;
e) zero σ, three π&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To form a molecule with a trigonal bipyramidal electron geometry, what set of pure atomic orbitals must be mixed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) one s and three p&lt;br /&gt;
b) one s, three p, and one d&lt;br /&gt;
c) one s, three p, and two d&lt;br /&gt;
d) two s, six p, and two d&lt;br /&gt;
e) two s, six p, and four d  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the maximum number of hybridized orbitals formed by a fluorine atom?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1&lt;br /&gt;
b) 2&lt;br /&gt;
c) 3&lt;br /&gt;
d) 4&lt;br /&gt;
e) 6&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of either carbon atom in acetylene, C2H2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of the nitrogen atom in NCl3?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of the xenon atom in XeF2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of the central nitrogen atom in nitrite ion, NO2-?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of the chlorine atom in chlorite ion, ClO2-?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of the central atom in a molecule with a square-planar molecular geometry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: e&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of each carbon atom in benzene, C6H6? Benzene contains a six-member carbon ring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For which of the following molecules does the central carbon atom have sp2 hybridization?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Cl2CO&lt;br /&gt;
b) CHCl3&lt;br /&gt;
c) CS2&lt;br /&gt;
d) CH2Cl2&lt;br /&gt;
e) HCN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For which of the following molecules and ions does the central nitrogen atom have sp3 hybridization?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) NO2-&lt;br /&gt;
b) HNO3&lt;br /&gt;
c) NOBr&lt;br /&gt;
d) NBr3&lt;br /&gt;
e) HNO2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For which of the following molecules and ions does the central atom have sp hybridization: NO2+, O3, and I3-?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) NO2+ only&lt;br /&gt;
b) O3 only&lt;br /&gt;
c) I3- only&lt;br /&gt;
d) O3 and I3-&lt;br /&gt;
e) I3- and NO2+&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the molecular geometry around a central atom that is sp3 hybridized and has two lone pairs of electrons?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) bent&lt;br /&gt;
b) linear&lt;br /&gt;
c) trigonal-planar&lt;br /&gt;
d) trigonal-pyramidal&lt;br /&gt;
e) trigonal-bipyramidal  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the molecular geometry around a central atom that is sp3d2 hybridized and has one lone pair of electrons?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) tetrahedral&lt;br /&gt;
b) trigonal-bipyramidal&lt;br /&gt;
c) square-planar&lt;br /&gt;
d) square-pyramidal&lt;br /&gt;
e) see-saw  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the molecular geometry around a central atom that is sp2 hybridized, has three sigma bonds, and one pi bond?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) trigonal-planar&lt;br /&gt;
b) trigonal-pyramidal&lt;br /&gt;
c) bent&lt;br /&gt;
d) T-shaped&lt;br /&gt;
e) tetrahedral  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the molecular geometry around a central atom that is sp3d hybridized and has one lone pair of eletrons?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) trigonal bipyramidal&lt;br /&gt;
b) trigonal-pyramidal&lt;br /&gt;
c) see-saw&lt;br /&gt;
d) tetrahedral&lt;br /&gt;
e) square-planar  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the hybridization of a central atom that has four sigma bonds and has no lone pairs of electrons?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp3d&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp3d2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon heating, CaCO3 decomposes to CaO and CO2. What change in the hybridization of carbon occurs in this reaction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp to sp2&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2 to sp3&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3 to sp&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp2 to sp&lt;br /&gt;
e) no change&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One product of the combustion of ethane, C2H6, is carbon dioxide. What change in hybridization of the carbon occurs in this reaction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp3 to sp2&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp3 to sp&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp2 to sp3&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp2 to sp3d2&lt;br /&gt;
e) sp2 to sp&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nitric acid, HNO3, dissociates in water to form nitrate ions and hydronium ions. What change in hybridization of the nitrogen atom occurs in this dissociation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) sp2 to sp3&lt;br /&gt;
b) sp2 to sp&lt;br /&gt;
c) sp3 to sp&lt;br /&gt;
d) sp to sp3&lt;br /&gt;
e) no change  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: e&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following hybridized atoms is not possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) an sp hybridized carbon atom&lt;br /&gt;
b) an sp2 hybridized sulfur atom&lt;br /&gt;
c) an sp3 hybridized phosphorus atom&lt;br /&gt;
d) an sp3d hybridized oxygen atom&lt;br /&gt;
e) an sp3d2 hybridized xenon atom  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following characteristics apply to SO2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;polar bonds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;nonpolar molecule&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;linear molecular shape&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sp hybridized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1 only&lt;br /&gt;
b) 1 and 2&lt;br /&gt;
c) 3 and 4&lt;br /&gt;
d) 1, 2, and 3&lt;br /&gt;
e) 1, 2, 3, and 4&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dichloromethane, CH2Cl2, is a common organic solvent. Which of the following statements concerning dichloromethane is/are CORRECT?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH2Cl2 has two isomers. For one isomer of CH2Cl2, the chlorine atoms are adjacent to each other and the molecule is polar. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH2Cl2 has two isomers. For one isomer of CH2Cl2, the chlorine atoms are on opposites sides of the carbon atom and the molecule is nonpolar. &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The hybridization of the central carbon atom is sp3.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1 only&lt;br /&gt;
b) 2 only&lt;br /&gt;
c) 3 only&lt;br /&gt;
d) 1 and 2&lt;br /&gt;
e) 1, 2, and 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;molecular-orbital-theory&quot;&gt;9.3 Molecular Orbital Theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the following statements concerning molecular orbital (MO) theory are correct EXCEPT&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) the Pauli exclusion principle is obeyed.&lt;br /&gt;
b) Hund’s rule is obeyed.&lt;br /&gt;
c) electrons are assigned to orbitals of successively higher energy.&lt;br /&gt;
d) a bonding molecular orbital is lower in energy than its parent atomic orbitals.&lt;br /&gt;
e) the combination of two atomic orbitals creates only one molecular orbital.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: e&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atomic orbitals combine most effectively to form molecular orbitals when&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) electrons in the orbitals have no spins.&lt;br /&gt;
b) electrons in the orbitals have the same spin.&lt;br /&gt;
c) the atomic orbitals are hybridized.&lt;br /&gt;
d) the atomic orbitals have similar energies.&lt;br /&gt;
e) p-orbitals are half-filled.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A molecular orbital that decreases the electron density between two nuclei is said to be &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;__.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) hybridized&lt;br /&gt;
b) bonding&lt;br /&gt;
c) antibonding&lt;br /&gt;
d) pi-bonding&lt;br /&gt;
e) nonpolar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following molecular orbital diagram may be used for problems 35-48. For oxygen and fluorine, the σ2p orbital should be lower in energy than the π2p. However, the diagram will still yield correct bond order and magnetic behavior for these molecules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;↑ Energy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;	________	σ*2p
	
________		________	π*2p
	
	________	σ2p
	
________		________	π2p
	
	________	σ*2s
	
	________	σ2s
	
	________	σ*1s
	
	________	σ1s
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;35: According to molecular orbital theory, which of the following species is the most likely to exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) H22-&lt;br /&gt;
b) He2&lt;br /&gt;
c) Li22-&lt;br /&gt;
d) Be2&lt;br /&gt;
e) Be22-  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: e&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;36:	According to molecular orbital theory, which of the following species is least likely to exist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Be2&lt;br /&gt;
b) F22+&lt;br /&gt;
c) C22-&lt;br /&gt;
d) Li2&lt;br /&gt;
e) B22-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;37:	According to molecular orbital theory, which of the following species has the highest bond order?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) F2&lt;br /&gt;
b) F22+&lt;br /&gt;
c) C22-&lt;br /&gt;
d) Li2&lt;br /&gt;
e) B22+&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;38:	According to molecular orbital theory, what is the bond order of oxygen, O2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1&lt;br /&gt;
b) 3/2&lt;br /&gt;
c) 2&lt;br /&gt;
d) 5/2&lt;br /&gt;
e) 3  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;39:	According to molecular orbital theory, what is the bond order of N2-?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1&lt;br /&gt;
b) 3/2&lt;br /&gt;
c) 2&lt;br /&gt;
d) 5/2&lt;br /&gt;
e) 3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;40:	According to molecular orbital theory, which of the following lists ranks the oxygen species in terms of increasing bond order? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) O22+ &amp;lt; O22- &amp;lt; O2&lt;br /&gt;
b) O22- &amp;lt; O2 &amp;lt; O22+&lt;br /&gt;
c) O2 &amp;lt; O22+ &amp;lt; O22-&lt;br /&gt;
d) O2 &amp;lt; O22- &amp;lt; O22+&lt;br /&gt;
e) O22+ &amp;lt; O2 &amp;lt; O22-  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;41:	Consider the molecules B2, C2, N2 and O2. Which two molecules have the same bond order?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) B2 and C2&lt;br /&gt;
b) B2 and O2&lt;br /&gt;
c) C2 and N2&lt;br /&gt;
d) C2 and O2&lt;br /&gt;
e) N2 and O2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;42:	Use molecular orbital theory to predict which species is paramagnetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) N2&lt;br /&gt;
b) O2&lt;br /&gt;
c) F2&lt;br /&gt;
d) Li2&lt;br /&gt;
e) H2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;43:	Use molecular orbital theory to predict which ion is paramagnetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) F22+&lt;br /&gt;
b) O22-&lt;br /&gt;
c) O22+&lt;br /&gt;
d) N22+&lt;br /&gt;
e) B22-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;44:	What is the molecular orbital configuration of F2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (σ2p)2 (σ&lt;/em&gt;2p)2&lt;br /&gt;
b) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)2 (σ2p)2 (π&lt;/em&gt;2p)2&lt;br /&gt;
c) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (π&lt;/em&gt;2p)4&lt;br /&gt;
d) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (σ2p)2 (π&lt;/em&gt;2p)6&lt;br /&gt;
e) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (σ2p)2 (π&lt;/em&gt;2p)4  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: e&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;45:	What is the molecular orbital configuration of N22+?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (σ2p)2 (π&lt;/em&gt;2p)2&lt;br /&gt;
b) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4&lt;br /&gt;
c) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;/em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)2 (σ2p)2&lt;br /&gt;
d) [core electrons] (σ2s)4 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)4&lt;br /&gt;
e) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;/em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (σ2p)2(π*2p)4  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;46:	Assume that the molecular orbital energy diagram for a homonuclear diatomic molecule applies to a heteronuclear diatomic molecule. What is the molecular orbital configuration of NO?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (σ2p)2 (π&lt;/em&gt;2p)1&lt;br /&gt;
b) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)2 (σ2p)2 (π&lt;/em&gt;2p)2&lt;br /&gt;
c) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)2 (σ2p)3&lt;br /&gt;
d) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ&lt;/em&gt;2s)2 (π2p)4 (σ2p)1&lt;br /&gt;
e) [core electrons] (σ2s)2 (σ*2s)2 (π2p)2  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: a&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;47:	Assuming that the molecular orbital energy diagram for a homonuclear diatomic molecule applies to a heteronuclear diatomic molecule, determine which of the following species has the highest bond order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) NO-&lt;br /&gt;
b) OF-&lt;br /&gt;
c) CN-&lt;br /&gt;
d) O2&lt;br /&gt;
e) NO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;48:	Assuming that the molecular orbital energy diagram for a homonuclear diatomic molecule applies to a heteronuclear diatomic molecule, determine which of the following species is paramagnetic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) NO+&lt;br /&gt;
b) CO&lt;br /&gt;
c) CN-&lt;br /&gt;
d) OF-&lt;br /&gt;
e) NO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: e&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the NO2- ion, each atom can be viewed as sp2 hybridized. Thus, each atom has one remaining unhybridized p orbital. How many π2p molecular orbitals (including both bonding and antibonding orbitals) are formed using the unhybridized p orbitals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) 1&lt;br /&gt;
b) 3&lt;br /&gt;
c) 4&lt;br /&gt;
d) 6&lt;br /&gt;
e) 12  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: b&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benzene, C6H6, consists of a six member ring of sp2 hybridized carbon atoms. Each carbon atom has one unhybridized p orbital. How many π2p bonding, antibonding, and nonbonding molecular orbitals exist for benzene?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) Three π2p molecular orbitals exist; two bonding and one antibonding.&lt;br /&gt;
b) Three π2p molecular orbitals exist; one bonding, one antibonding, and one nonbonding.&lt;br /&gt;
c) Six π2p molecular orbitals exist; three bonding and three antibonding.&lt;br /&gt;
d) Six π2p molecular orbitals exist; two bonding, two nonbonding, and two antibonding.&lt;br /&gt;
e) Twelve π2p molecular orbitals exist; six bonding and six antibonding.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: c&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;short-answer-questions&quot;&gt;Short Answer Questions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which theory, valence bond or molecule orbital, correctly predicts the existence of paramagnetic molecules?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: molecular orbital theory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In valence bond theory, each sigma bond in CH4 is formed from the overlap of a hydrogen atom’s 1s orbital with a &lt;em&gt;__&lt;/em&gt; hybridized orbital on the carbon atom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: sp3&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In molecular orbital theory, the bond order is defined as 1/2(the number of electrons in &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;__ orbitals minus the number of electrons in antibonding orbitals).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: bonding&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triiodide ion, I3-, has a trigonal-bipyramidal electron-pair geometry and a linear molecular geometry. The hybridization of the central iodine atom is &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;__.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: sp3d&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hybridization of the xenon atom in XeOF4 is &lt;strong&gt;__&lt;/strong&gt;__.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: sp3d2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mathsci.co//chemistry/chap-9-review/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mathsci.co//chemistry/chap-9-review/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry I - Unit 4 Exam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If the change in internal energy for a given process is zero, which of the following must be true?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;q = -w &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;w = 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆E = ∆H&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;q = 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
∆E = q + w = 0&lt;br /&gt;
q = -w&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon monoxide reacts with oxygen to form carbon dioxide by the following reaction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 CO(g) + O2(g) → 2 CO2(g)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;∆H for this reaction is −135.28 kcal.&lt;br /&gt;
If 811.7 kcal is released, how many moles of CO must have reacted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12.0 mol &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16.3 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6.00 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;270.5 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.35 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;40.5 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5.41 mol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At constant temperature and pressure, how is ∆Suniv related to ∆Gsys?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Gsys = ∆Suniv&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Gsys = −T ∆Suniv &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Gsys = −∆Suniv&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Gsys = T ∆Suniv&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Gsys = − ∆Suniv / T&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Gsys = ∆Suniv / T&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 22.9 g sample of metal X requires 136 calories of energy to heat it from 10.0◦C to 81.0◦C. Calculate the specific heat of metal X.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2615&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.21&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2548&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2038&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.3562&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.3902&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.3081&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2187&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.35&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.2733&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correct answer: 0.35 J/g ·◦ C.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chlorine monofluoride (ClF) will react with carbon monoxide (CO) to give carbonyl chlorofluoride (COClF):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ClF + CO −→ COClF&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use bond energies (provided elsewhere) to estimate the change in enthalpy (∆H) for this reaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-298 kJ/mol &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-571 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-444 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-376 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-193 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the change in entropy (∆Svap) for the vaporization of ethanol (∆Hvap = 38.6 kJ · mol−1) at its standard boiling temperature (78.4 ◦C)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;−110 J · mol−1 · K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;−492 J · mol−1 · K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;492J·mol−1 ·K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;110 J · mol−1 · K−1 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that ∆fH◦Fe2O3(s) = −826 kJ mol−1 what would you predict for the spontaneity of the following reaction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2Fe2O3(s) → 4Fe(s) + 3O2(g)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is no way to predict the spontaneity of this reaction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it would be spontaneous only at high temperatures &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it would never be spontaneous&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it would be spontaneous at all temperatures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it would be spontaneous only at low temperatures&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The reaction as written is the reverse of twice the formation of Fe2O3. As such this reaction is extremely endothermic (∆H » 0). However, the entropy change for this reaction should be positive as it generates three moles of gas. The enthalpy changes cause an increase in the free energy, but the entropy change will cause the free energy to decrease. At high temperatures the entropy will dominate and the free energy change will be negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following is always true for a spontaneous process at constant temperature?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆S = q / T&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆S &amp;gt; 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Ssystem + ∆Ssurroundings &amp;gt; 0 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆S &amp;lt; q / T&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆Ssystem + ∆Ssurroundings = q / T&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The entropy of a system or its surroundings may increase or decrease. The Second Law of Thermodynamics states that in spontaneous changes, the universe tends toward a state of greater disorder; that is, entropy increases (∆S &amp;gt; 0).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rank the following systems by entropy, from least to greatest:
a) 1 mol of pure ice
b) 1 mol of water with 1 mol of salt dissolved in it.
c) 1 mol of pure water&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;c &amp;lt; b &amp;lt; a&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &amp;lt; b &amp;lt; c&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;c &amp;lt; a &amp;lt; b&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;b &amp;lt; c &amp;lt; a&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;b &amp;lt; a &amp;lt; c&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a &amp;lt; c &amp;lt; b &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Entropy increases as systems go through endothermic phase transitions and when there is more matter or more dispersed matter present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the reaction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ni(s) + 4 CO(g) → Ni(CO)4(g)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming the gases are ideal, calculate the work done on the system at a constant pressure of 1 atm at 75◦C for the conversion of 1.00 mole of Ni to Ni(CO)4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.89 × 103 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5.79 × 103 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.80 × 103 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.87 × 103 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.16 × 104 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8.68 × 103 J &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the standard enthalpy of combustion (∆cH) of t-butyl acetate, C6H12O2(l).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-125 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-4080 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-4635 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-3525 kJ/mol &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-2970 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-4371 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-3261 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The balanced equation is:&lt;br /&gt;
C6H12O2(l) + 8O2(g) → 6CO2(g) + 6H2O(l)&lt;br /&gt;
∆cH = 6(−394) + 6(−286) − (−555)&lt;br /&gt;
∆cH = −2364 + −1716 + 555&lt;br /&gt;
∆cH = −3525&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the entropy change for the system when 40 g of ethanol are heated from 25◦C to 40◦C given that the heat capacity for ethanol is 2.44 J g−1 K−1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4.8 J K−1 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-45.9 J K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.12 J K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;45.9 J K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-2.3 J K−1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the reaction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2 SO2(g) + O2(g) → 2 SO3(g)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which statement is true for this reaction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆S &amp;lt; 0 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sm◦ = 0 for O2(g)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆S &amp;gt; 0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;∆S = 0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For the reaction 3 mol gas → 2 mol gas. The fewer the moles of gas, the lower the disorder, so ∆S is negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the standard reaction enthalpy for the reaction&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NO2(g) → NO(g) + O(g)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given:&lt;br /&gt;
O2(g) → 2 O(g)&lt;br /&gt;
∆H◦ = +498.4 kJ/mol&lt;br /&gt;
NO(g) + O3(g) → NO2(g) + O2(g)&lt;br /&gt;
∆H◦ = −200 kJ/mol&lt;br /&gt;
3O2(g) → 2 O3(g) .&lt;br /&gt;
∆H◦ = +285.4 kJ/mol  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;+306 kJ/mol &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;+555 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;+192 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;+355 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;+93.5 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;+413 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;+592 kJ/mol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is ∆Suniv for a reaction conducted at 100◦C and for which ∆S is 170 J · mol−1 · K−1 and ∆H is 43.2 kJ · mol−1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;−262 J · mol−1 · K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;285.8 J · mol−1 · K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;602 J · mol−1 ·K−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;54.2 J · mol−1 · K−1 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
∆Suniv = ∆Ssys + ∆Ssurr&lt;br /&gt;
= 170 J · mol−1 · K−1&lt;br /&gt;
− 43200 J · mol−1 373 K&lt;br /&gt;
= 54.2 J · mol−1 · K−1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following reactions as written corresponds to a standard formation reaction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SO2(g) + 1/2 O2(g) → SO3(g)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2H (g) + O2(g) → H2O2 (l)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Na(s) + 1/2 Cl2(g) → NaCl(s) &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 H2(g) + O2(g) → 2 H2O(l)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CO2(s) → CO2(g)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
All of the reactants in a formation reaction must be ELEMENTS in their thermochemical standard state. AND, to match table values, only 1 MOLE of product can be formed because standard table values are in kJ/mol. Only the NaCl fits this definition. The H2O reaction unfortunately is forming 2 moles of water instead of one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enthalpy of fusion of methanol (CH3OH) is 3.16 kJ/mol. How much heat would be absorbed or released upon freezing 25.6 grams of methanol?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.253 kJ absorbed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3.95 kJ absorbed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.52 kJ absorbed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.253 kJ released&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3.95 kJ released&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.52 kJ released &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
MW CH3OH = 32.042g&lt;br /&gt;
∆H(fusion) = −∆H(freezing)&lt;br /&gt;
q = 25.6 g × (1 mol / 32.042 g mol) × (−3.16 kJ / mol)&lt;br /&gt;
= −2.525 kJ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sample of 2 grams of compound Y is burned completely in a bomb calorimeter which contains 2500 g of water. The temperature rises from 25.529◦C to 25.991◦C. What is ∆Urxn for the combustion of compound Y? The hardware component of the calorimeter has a heat capacity of 3.78 kJ/◦C. The specific heat of water is 4.184 J/g·◦C, and the MW of Y is 129 g/mol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-311.8&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-572.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-503.5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-235.9&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-424.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-213.5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-165.2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-552.3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-269.5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;-335.2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correct answer: −424.3 kJ/mol of Y.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sodium is a metal that reacts violently with water. Chlorine is a toxic, choking gas. So it’s a really good thing that when you put salt on your fries (chips) that it doesnt suddenly turn into sodium metal and chlorine gas. Why is this the case?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The standard enthalpy of formation of sodium chloride is negative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The standard Gibbs free energy of formation of sodium chloride is negative. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The standard entropy change for the formation of sodium chloride is negative.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salt dissolves in the water in your food. 5. Salt has a really high melting point.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The standard Gibbs free energy of formation of sodium chloride is negative so the process is spontaneous. Thus ’unforming’ sodium chloride is nonspontaneous, so sodium chloride is stable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-4-exam/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-4-exam/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry I - Unit 3 Exam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Select the FALSE statement about compounds with octahedral geometries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The central atom in compounds with octahedral geometries always obey the octet rule. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compounds with octahedral geometries do not have eight atoms bonded to the central atom.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Octahedral electronic geometries may have four atoms bonded to the central atom.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If a compound has a square planar molecular geometry, it corresponds to an octahedral electronic geometry.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Angles in compounds with octahedral molecular geometries are typically 90 and 180 degrees.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Octahedral molecular geometries always require sp3d2 hybridizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Compounds with octahedral geometries have expanded valence shells. These are exceptions to the octet rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SO2−4 is more/less polar than SO2−3 because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more; the tetrahedral geometry increases the polarity of S – O bonds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more; it has four polar S – O bonds rather than three polar S – O bonds.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;less; the four polar S – O bonds in SO2−4 are symmetrical and cancel the dipole moments. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;less; it is a resonance structure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;more; the four polar S – O bonds in SO2−4 are arranged non-symmetrically leaving
a net dipole moment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
SO2−4 has no lone pairs on the central S atom. It has tetrahedral molecular geometry. Each bond angle is 109.5◦. The dipole moments cancel and the molecule is non-polar.&lt;br /&gt;
SO2−3 has one lone pair on the central S atom. It has pyramidal molecular geometry. The bond angles are not equal so the dipole moments cannot cancel. This molecule is polar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For which of the following is the type of solid INCORRECTLY given?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C6H6, molecular solid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KF, ionic solid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H2O, molecular solid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ni, metallic solid&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CsI, covalent solid &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
CsI is an ionic solid. An ionic bond is a bond between a cation 􏰀Cs+1􏰁 and an anion
􏰀I−1􏰁.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A substance has a melting point of 1200 K. It conducts electricity while melting but not in the solid. This substance would be classified as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a metallic solid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an ionic solid. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a covalent network solid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a hydrogen bonded solid.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a molecular solid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ionic solids are held together by electrostatic attractions between cations and anions. In a melted phase, the ions can move and therefore can carry current.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the molecule CF4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has four non-polar bonds and is a non-polar molecule.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has four polar bonds and is a polar molecule.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has four anti-bonds and is a polar bear.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has four non-polar bonds and is a polar molecule.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has four polar bonds and is a non-polar molecule. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Fluorine has a very high electronegativity when compared to carbon. A covalent bond between two molecules with such different electronegativities is polar. The molecular geometry of the molecule CF4 is tetrahedral, and all the bonds have an equal dipole moment since they are all between the same atoms (C and F). The net dipole of the molecule is zero since all of the individual dipoles cancel each other out. A molecule with no net dipole moment is non-polar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a molecule of AB2 has 2 lone pairs of electrons on A, what would you expect the B-A-B angle to be closest to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;62.5 degrees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;109.5 degrees &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;90 degrees&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;120 degrees&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This molecule fits the general formula AB2U2. These structures, which have 4 regions of high electron density, have tetrahedral electronic geometries, and they have bond angles close to 109.5 degrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What structural feature makes unsaturated fats less rigid than saturated fats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsaturated fats have weaker covalent bonds along the chain; weaker covalent bonds result in reduced rigidity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsaturated fats have a bend that reduces the strength and number of dispersion forces between molecules. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The statement is untrue; saturated fats are more rigid because their C-C bond lengths are shorter and stronger than for unsaturated fats.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The statement is untrue; saturated fats are more rigid because of their higher molecular weight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Unsaturated fats have at least one double bond. Along the fatty acid chain, there is a bend at each double bond. (Imagine an elbow.) Packing of such fats is less dense at the molecular level, and fewer dispersion forces are possible. This results in a less rigid substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bonding in metals like tin and lead is best described as (localized, delocalized) whereas the bonding in insulators or semiconductors (such as diamond or silicon) is best described as (localized, delocalized).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delocalized; localized &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;localized; localized&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delocalized; delocalized&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;localized; delocalized&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Metallic solids are solids composed of metal atoms that are held together by metallic bonds. These bonds are like huge molecular orbitals that span across the whole solid. Electrons are not just held between a few of atoms in a sigma bond. Rather, there is a sea of electrons everywhere. In covalent, molecular, and ionic solids, electrons are localized in bonds between atoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use VSEPR theory to predict the shape of the molecule SeF6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;linear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;None of these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;bent or angular&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trigonal-pyramidal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tetrahedral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trigonal-bipyramidal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;octahedral &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trigonal-planar&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following are important contributions that MO theory makes to chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I. The ability to use MO theory with a computer to calculate the minimum energy geometry of a molecule.&lt;br /&gt;
II. The ability to predict the energy at which a molecule will absorb light.&lt;br /&gt;
III. The ability to predict whether or not a molecule should be paramagnetic or diamagnetic.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only I&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I and II&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I, II, and III &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only II&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;none of them&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;II and III&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The MO theory is a powerful theory that, based on Quantum mechanical calculations, and with the help of a powerful computer, can very quickly calculate the energies of electrons in a small or large molecule as the relative positions of the atoms of the molecule are moved relative to each other. This iterative calculation results in the lowest energy arrangement of all the atoms and all the electrons of the atoms in the molecule, thus leading to the prediction of the most likely arrangement of the atoms and electrons. Therefore, the shape, magnetism (pair or unpaired electrons residing in orbitals), and the energy difference of the HOMO and LUMO can be calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following combinations of hybridization and molecular geometry is not possible?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sp3; tetrahedral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sp2; angular&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sp3d; linear&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sp3d2; octahedral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sp3d2; angular &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sp3; angular&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Angular molecular geometries can only be formed from sp2 and sp3 hybridizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A molecule with tetrahedral geometry must be nonpolar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;False &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;True&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which molecular geometries can stem from tetrahedral electronic geometry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trigonal pyramidal, seesaw&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tetrahedral, trigonal bipyramidal, linear, angular, seesaw&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tetrahedral, trigonal pyramidal, angular &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;only tetrahedral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;tetrahedral, T-shaped, linear&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tetrahedral, trigonal pyramidal and angular are three molecular geometries that can stem from tetrahedral electronic geometry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following molecules is incorrectly matched with molecular geometry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NH3 : tetrahedral &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H2O : angular&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;AsF5 : trigonal bipyramidal&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;TeF6 : octahedral&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SiF4 : tetrahedral&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The &lt;em&gt;electronic&lt;/em&gt; geometry of NH3 is tetrahedral, but its &lt;em&gt;molecular&lt;/em&gt; geometry is trigonal pyramidal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which represents a false statement?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All molecules with four regions of electron density have sp3 hybridization.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The sp2 hybridization corresponds to trigonal planar electronic arrangements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All square planar molecules have octahedral electronic arrangements.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All angular molecules are sp2 hybridized. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Angular molecules can be sp2 or sp3 hybridized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are all of the intermolecular forces that are responsible for the existence of ice?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dipole-dipole and London forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dipole-dipole and ion-ion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;hydrogen bonding and dipole-dipole&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;London forces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dipole-dipole, London forces, and hydrogen bonding &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ice is solid H2O. This molecule exhibits dispersion. Because it is polar it also exhibits dipole-dipole interactions. Finally because of the H bonded to the electronegative O atom it also exhibits hydrogen bonding; this polar bond can orient and interact with the lone pair of an O atom on another H2O molecule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following molecules would be expected to have the lowest boiling point?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C2H6&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C12H26&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C8H18&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH4 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;C16H34&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
These molecules are all very similar in that they are made up only of hydrogen and carbon. They are all covalently bonded, nonpolar, and cannot form hydrogen bonds. Therefore the only intermolecular force that attracts these molecules to each other are dispersion forces. Dispersion forces are generally stronger for molecules that have more electrons or are larger, so you would predict that the smallest molecule in this group (CH4) would have the weakest intermolecular forces and thus would have the lowest boiling point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A molecule with a central atom and two bonded atoms is bent with a bond angle of 117◦. Assuming the central atom satisfies the octet rule, how many lone pairs does it have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3 lone pairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 lone pair &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2 lone pairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0 lone pairs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4 lone pairs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Only a molecule with two singly bonded atoms and one lone pair (a pair of nonbonding electrons) would satisfy all of the constraints laid out in the problem, most notably the bond angle which implies trigonal planar geometry and thus 3 regions of high electron density (RHED). Since two of these are atoms, the third must be a lone pair. Example: NOH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following has the highest vapor pressure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH3CH2OH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH3CH2COOH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH3CH2OCH2CH3 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH3OH&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H2O&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The compound with the highest vapor pressure will be the one that most readily evaporates (the one with the weakest intermolecular forces). All of the choices exhibit London (van der Waals) forces and are also polar, so they can exhibit dipole-dipole interactions. However, unlike the other choices, CH3CH2OCH2CH3 does not have O – H bonds and so cannot exhibit hydrogen bonding. Although CH3CH2OCH2CH3 is the largest molecule, the higher London forces are not strong enough to counteract the lack of hydrogen bonding so overall it has the weakest intermolecular forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-3-exam/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-3-exam/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry I - Unit 2 Exam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Which of the following statements is true regarding electromagnetic radiation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electromagnetic radiation with a wavelength of 400 nm has a frequency that is lower than that with a wavelength of 600 nm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electromagnetic radiation with a wavelength of 400 nm travels faster than that with a wavelength of 600 nm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electromagnetic radiation with a wavelength of 600 nm travels faster than that with a wavelength of 400 nm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Electromagnetic radiation with a wavelength of 600 nm has a frequency that is lower than that with a wavelength of 400 nm. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The frequency of electromagnetic radiation determines how fast it travels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
v=fλ, so λ=1. Higher wavelengths correspond to lower frequencies, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the frequency of a 500 nm photon?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9.0 × 10^−17 Hz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;15 Hz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4.0 × 10^−7 Hz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5.0 × 10^−6 Hz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.5 × 10^−16 Hz&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6.0 × 10^14 Hz &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
frequency = speed of light / wavelength = 3e8 / 500e-9 = 6e14&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which color in the rainbow has the shortest wavelength?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;green&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;blue &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;orange&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;red&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;yellow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ordered by wavelengths,
blue &amp;lt; green &amp;lt; yellow &amp;lt; orange &amp;lt; red&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An orbital with n = 4 and l = 2 would be described as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4s.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2p.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4d. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2s.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4p.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
l = 2 refers to the d orbital, so the orbital is 4d.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rank the following species from smallest to largest atomic radius: K, Mg, Rb, Ca.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mg &amp;lt; Rb &amp;lt; K &amp;lt; Ca&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mg &amp;lt; Ca &amp;lt; Rb &amp;lt; K&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mg &amp;lt; K &amp;lt; Ca &amp;lt; Rb&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mg &amp;lt; Ca &amp;lt; K &amp;lt; Rb &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rb &amp;lt; K &amp;lt; Ca &amp;lt; Mg&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Atomic radii increase down and to the left.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When two H atoms are brought together from large distances they can make H2. As the bond begins to form, the force between the atoms becomes more (attractive, repulsive) and the potential energy (increases, stays the same, decreases).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;attractive; increases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;attractive; decreases &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;attractive; stays the same&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;repulsive; increases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;repulsive; decreases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;repulsive; stays the same&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a pure covalent bond, electrons are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;uncharged.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared equally. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transferred.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared unequally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which compound is the bond the LEAST polar?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HCl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HBr&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HF&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HI &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number of single bonds, double bonds, triple bonds, and unshared (lone) pairs on the central atom in the sulfite ion (SO 2− 3) is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3,0,0,1 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2,1,0,0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1,1,0,2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1,2,0,1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2,1,0,1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To draw the dot structure for SO2−3 we must first calculate the number of valence electrons available from the atoms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A = 6 × 1 (S atom) + 6 × 3 (O atoms) + 2 (from −2 charge)&lt;br /&gt;
= 26 e−  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We choose the least electronegative element as the central atom (sulfur in this case) and place the other atoms symmetrically around it.&lt;br /&gt;
The correct dot structure for the molecule should show a complete octet (8 electrons) around each atom and a total of 26 valence electrons for the entire structure.&lt;br /&gt;
(If using the S = N − A rule to determine the dot structure, N = (8×1)+(8×3) = 32 e− and S = 32−26 = 6 e−. This would indicate 3 bonds and correspond to the structure shown above.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The carbon and oxygen in carbon monoxide (CO) are joined by what type of bond or bonds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;two double bonds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one triple bond &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one single bond&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;one double bond&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;four single bonds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The total number of valence electrons is&lt;br /&gt;
C 1×4e−= 4e−&lt;br /&gt;
O 1×6e−= 6e−&lt;br /&gt;
10 e−&lt;br /&gt;
and the Lewis dot structure is :C≣O:&lt;br /&gt;
The 3 lines represent a triple bond between the C and O.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Draw the Lewis electron dot structure for SO3. What is the total number of lone pairs of electrons on the three oxygen atoms?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;7&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To draw the dot structure for SO3 we must first calculate the number of valence electrons available from the atoms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A = 6 × 1(S atom) + 6 × 3(O atoms) = 24 e−&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We choose the least electronegative element as the central atom (sulfur in this case) and place the other atoms symmetrically around it.&lt;br /&gt;
The correct dot structure for the molecule should show a complete octet (8 electrons) around each atom and a total of 24 valence electrons for the entire structure.&lt;br /&gt;
(If using the S = N − A rule to determine thedotstructure,N =8×1+8×3=32e− and S = 32−24 = 8 e−. This would indicate 4 bonds and correspond to the structure shown above.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which one of the following compounds does NOT obey the octet rule?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CH4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;BF3 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NaCl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H2O&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many lone pairs are on the central atom of AsF5?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The chemical formula for potassium sulfate is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;K3(SO4)2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KSO4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;K(SO4)2&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;K2SO4 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
K+ and SO2−4 forms K2SO4:&lt;br /&gt;
2(+1) + 1(−2) = 0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an ionic compound, the lattice energy is the energy associated with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;generating the ionic compound from the neutral elements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dissolving the compound in water to form aqueous ions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;moving a pair of ions to infinite separa- tion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;breaking up the solid crystal into gas phase ions. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The lattice energy is the energy associated with taking the ions from the solid crystalline structure and separating them into ions in the gas phase. The energy associated with simply separating two isolated ions is the Coulomb energy. The energy for dissolving the compound to for aqueous ions is the enthalpy of solution. And the energy for forming the ionic compound from neutral elements is the enthalpy of formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the first three energy levels for an electron in a helium ion.&lt;br /&gt;
1st energy level : −6.41 × 10−19 J&lt;br /&gt;
2nd energy level : −1.60 × 10−19 J&lt;br /&gt;
3rd energy level : −0.72 × 10−19 J&lt;br /&gt;
A 413 nm photon interacts with the ion. What might happen as a result of this in- teraction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An electron could be excited from the 2nd to 3rd energy level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An electron could be excited from the 1st to 3rd energy level.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;None of the transitions listed would occur.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An electron could be excited from the 1st to 2nd energy level. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following is NOT correctly matched name to formula&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;diselenium oxide SeO2 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;phosphorus pentachloride PCl5 3. sulfur trioxide SO3&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;carbon tetrachloride CCl4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;dinitrogen pentoxide N2O5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
SeO2 is selenium dioxide.&lt;br /&gt;
The prefix lable ”di” is misplaced in the answer indicating a ratio of 2:1 Se to O.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The oxygen/oxygen bond in O2 is stronger than in HOOH because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the oxygen/oxygen bond in O2 is more polar than in HOOH.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;O2 has a oxygen/oxygen double bond and HOOH has a oxygen/oxygen single bond. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;O2 has only one structure, while HOOH has a resonance structure that weakens the bond.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;O2 has an oxygen/oxgyen triple bond where HOOH has an oxygen/oxygen double bond.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;O2 has a resonance structure that pro- vides extra stability compared to the HOOH which has only one contributing structure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the oxygen/oxygen bond in O2 is less polar than in HOOH.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The Lewis dot structure of O2 shows it has a oxygen/oxygen double bond. HOOH only has a oxygen/oxygen single bond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following species is isoelectronic with S2− ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Br−&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As3−&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rb+&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mg2+&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ar &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Isoelectronic means ‘has the same number of electrons as’. Locate each element in the Periodic Table. The atomic number will give the number of protons, which equals the number of electrons for the neutral atom; for an ion, you will have to add or subtract from this value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let X be a hypothetical element.&lt;br /&gt;
Which of the following would be largest?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X2+&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X−&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X2− &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;X+&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
X2− would be largest as it has 2 more electrons than protons, and the protons here would be at the greatest disadvantage when trying to draw the electrons towards the nucleus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cobalt-60 (60 27 Co) is an artificial radioisotope that is produced in a nuclear reactor for use as a gamma-ray source in the treatment of certain types of cancer. If the wavelength of the gamma radiation from a cobalt-60 source is 1.00 × 10−3 nm, calculate the energy of a photon of this radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.0 × 10−13 J &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.0 × 10−16 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.0 × 10−19 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6.4 × 10−14 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;None of these&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6.63 × 10−34 J&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6.4 × 10−10 J&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
λ = 1.00 × 10−3 nm&lt;br /&gt;
Ephoton = ?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ephoton = h ν = hc / λ&lt;br /&gt;
= (6.626 × 10−34 J · s)(3.0 × 108 m/s) / (1.00 × 10−3 nm)(10−9 m/nm)&lt;br /&gt;
= 2.0 × 10−13 J&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An electron in a hydrogen atom moves from the n = 2 to n = 5 level. What is the wavelength of the photon that corresponds to this transition and is the photon emitted or absorbed during this process?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;276 nm; absorbed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1875 nm; absorbed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1875 nm; emitted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;434 nm; emitted&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;434 nm; absorbed &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;276 nm; emitted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following is correct with respect to the photoelectric effect?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A plot of the kinetic energy of the ejected electrons versus the frequency of the incident radiation has a slope that is equal to the value of the work function.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The kinetic energy of the ejected electrons increases with the intensity of the incident radiation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A plot of the kinetic energy of the ejected electrons versus the frequency of the incident radiation is linear. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All metals have the same work function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The photoelectric effect is summarized by&lt;br /&gt;
KE=hν−φ, which fits the standard equation for a line :&lt;br /&gt;
y=mx−c,&lt;br /&gt;
where φ is the work function of the metal, and varies for different metals. The intensity of the incident radiation does not show here as it is just the number of photons hitting a surface in a given time.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You shine white light through a sample of neon atoms and then through a holographic diffraction grating. From this experiment, you would expect to observe  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;mostly black space with thin lines of color.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a continuous spectrum broken by thin black lines. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a continuous spectrum.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phosphorus has a higher ionization energy than silicon because&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;False; phosphorus has a lower ionization energy than silicon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the outer orbitals of phosphorus are located closer to the nucleus than the outer orbitals of silicon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the effective nuclear charge of phosphorus is less than that of silicon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the outer orbitals of phosphorus are located farther from the nucleus than the outer orbitals of silicon.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the effective nuclear charge of silicon is less than that of phosphorus. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which of the following will not have ionic bonds?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NaCl&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;methane (CH4) &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;calcium oxide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;KBr&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;magnesium chloride&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
All of the options except CH4 have ionic bonds, which are formed between metals and nonmetals. CH4 has only covalent (nonmetal-nonmetal) bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any neutral atom having an odd (i.e., uneven) atomic number must be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;metallic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;non-magnetic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;paramagnetic. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;inert.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a transition element.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-2-exam/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-2-exam/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Chemistry I - Unit 1 Exam</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The pressure on a gas at −68◦C is doubled, but its volume is held constant. What will the final temperature be in degrees Celsius?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;151.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;123.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;117.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;161.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;137.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;185.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;187.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;127.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;119.0  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;177.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correct answer: 137◦C.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same number of grams of NH3 and O2 are placed in separate bulbs of equal volume and temperature under conditions when both gases behave ideally. Which statement is true?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pressure in the O2 bulb is greater than the pressure in the NH3 bulb.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Both bulbs contain the same number of moles of gas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The bulb containing O2 contains more molecules of gas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pressures in the two bulbs are the same.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The pressure in the NH3 bulb is greater than the pressure in the O2 bulb. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The molecular weight of NH3 is less than that of O2, so in equal masses there are more moles of NH3 than of O2. At the same volume and temperature, the larger number of moles of NH3 would exert a higher pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Balance the equation&lt;br /&gt;
C2H6 + O2 → CO2 + H2O&lt;br /&gt;
using the smallest possible integers. The sum
of the coefficients is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;19 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;9&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A balanced equation must have the same number of each kind of atom on both sides of the equation. We find the number of each kind of atom using equation coefficients and composition stoichiometry. For example, we find there are 4 C atoms on the reactant side:&lt;br /&gt;
? C atoms = 2 C2H6 × 2C / 1 C2H6 = 4C.&lt;br /&gt;
The balanced equation is&lt;br /&gt;
2 C2H6 + 7 O2 → 4 CO2 + 6 H2O&lt;br /&gt;
and has 4C, 12H, and 14O atoms on each side.&lt;br /&gt;
? sum coefficients = 2 + 7 + 4 + 6 = 19  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the chemical reaction&lt;br /&gt;
2 H2O + energy → 2 H2 + O2  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;twice as much O2 as H2 will be produced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is no way to know how much of each will be produced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;equal amounts of H2 and O2 will be produced.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;twice as much H2 as O2 will be produced. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the following reaction:&lt;br /&gt;
CaCN2 + 3 H2O → CaCO3 + 2 NH3&lt;br /&gt;
105.0 g CaCN2 and 78.0 g H2O are reacted. Assuming 100% efficiency, which reactant is in excess and how much is leftover? The molar mass of CaCN2 is 80.11 g/mol. The molar mass of CaCO3 is 100.09 g/mol.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CaCN2; 7.20 g left over&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H2O; 10.7 g left over&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H2O; 7.20 g left over &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;H2O; 70.8 g left over&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CaCN2; 70.8 g left over&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CaCN2; 10.7 g left over&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
CaCN2 + 3 H2O → CaCO3 + 2 NH3&lt;br /&gt;
According to the stoichiometry 1 mol of CaCN2 reacts with 3 moles of H2O. First we calculate the moles of CaCN2 and of H2O as shown below.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;? mol CaCN2 = 105.0 g NaCN2 × 1 mol CaCN2 / 80.11 g CaCN2 = 1.31 mol CaCN2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;? molH2O = 78.0 g H2O × 1 mol H20 / 18.0152 g H2O = 4.33 mol H2O&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the stoichiometric ratio CaCN2 to H2O is 1 to 3, to react completely 1.31 mol CaCN2 we will require to use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3 × 1.31 = 3.93 mol H2O&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We calculated that we have 4.33 mol H2O. Therefore water is in excess:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4.33 − 3.93 = 0.40 mol H2O&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;? excess H2O = 0.40 mol H2O × 18.0152 g H2O / 1 mol H2O = 7.20 g H2O&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two gases are contained in gas bulbs connected by a valve. Gas A is present in a 36 L bulb at a pressure of 273 torr. Gas B exerts a pressure of 716 torr in a 84 L bulb. What is the partial pressure of gas B after they equilibrate once the valve has been opened?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;728.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;402.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;566.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;642.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;558.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;578.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;550.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;476.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;847.0&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;501.0&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correct answer: 501 torr.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
VA =36L&lt;br /&gt;
VB =84L&lt;br /&gt;
Vtotal =VA +VB =120L&lt;br /&gt;
PA =273torr&lt;br /&gt;
PB =716tor  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PBVB =PtVt  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pt = PB VB / Vt  = (716 torr) (84 L) / 120 L = 501 torr  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an improved version of the gas law, &lt;em&gt;V&lt;/em&gt; is replaced by (&lt;em&gt;V − n b&lt;/em&gt;). The two quantities &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt; in this equation represent, respectively, the&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;number of molecules; excluded molecular volume.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;number of moles; excluded molecular volume. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;number of moles; molecular radius.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;number of electrons; molecular radius.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;number of moles; the container size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; represents moles (as it does in &lt;em&gt;P V = nRT&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;b&lt;/em&gt; is the correction factor for volume because molecules really do take up space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ludwig Boltzmann performed a simple, but powerful experiment to gather evidence concerning the velocity distribution of a sample of gas particles. His experiment revealed that the velocities of gases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are distributed in a characteristic manner across a range of temperatures that depends on the molar mass of the gas, but not the temperature of the gas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are distributed in a characteristic manner across a range of temperatures that depends on the temperature of the gas, not the molar mass of the gas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are distributed in a characteristic manner across a range of temperatures that depends on the molar mass of the gas and the temper- ature of the gas. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are distributed in the same characteristic manner for all gases, regardless of the tem- perature or molar mass, as long as the gas is behaving ideally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider two balloons filled with gas and ar- ranged so that P, V , T are the same in both. The number of molecules in each balloon&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;could be different if the filling gases are different.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;would be the same only if the filling gases are the same.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;must be different.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;must be the same. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
P1 = P2&lt;br /&gt;
V1 = V2&lt;br /&gt;
T1 = T2&lt;br /&gt;
PV = nRT, so R = PV / nT
Thus&lt;br /&gt;
P2 V2 / n2 T2 = P1 V1 / n1 T1&lt;br /&gt;
n1 / n2 = P1V1T2 / P2V2T1 = 1&lt;br /&gt;
n1 = n2  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A steel tank containing helium is cooled to 15◦C. If you could look into the tank and see the gas molecules, what would you observe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The molecules would move to the center of the tank because their velocities would be lower, thus giving them less pressure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The gas molecules would become uniformly distributed near the entire wall of the tank because the molecules would try to escape the container due to their kinetic energies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The molecules would sink to the bottom of the tank because of the loss of pressure.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The gas molecules would still be uniformly distributed around the tank because gases expand to fill up the whole volume due to their constant molecular motion. correct&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The gas molecules would have higher kinetic energies and lower velocities, thus creating no net change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The average kinetic molecular energy would decrease, but since it is still in gas phase, the molecules would still expand uniformly to fill the tank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A gas sample occupies 3.59 L at 8.0◦C. What is the pressure given that there are 1.63 mol of gas in the sample?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10.6448&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6.05624&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;6.77834&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4.10406&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4.42826&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3.72675&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8.83326&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5.30303&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;4.9661&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10.4747&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correct answer: 10.4747 atm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;
n = 1.63 mol&lt;br /&gt;
V = 3.59L&lt;br /&gt;
T = 8.0◦C + 273 = 281K&lt;br /&gt;
P = ?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P = nRT/V&lt;br /&gt;
￼￼= (1.63 mol) 􏰀(0.0821 L·atm/mol·K) 􏰁(281 K) / (3.59 L)&lt;br /&gt;
  = 10.4747 atm  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The root mean square speed of nitrogen molecules in air at 20◦C is 511 m/s in a certain container. If the gas is allowed to expand to twice its original volume, the root mean square velocity of nitrogen molecules drops to 325 m/s. Calculate the temperature after the gas has expanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;−261◦C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;−347◦C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;347◦C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;154◦C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;261◦C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;45.1◦C&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;−154◦C &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;−45.1◦C&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If 250 mL of a gas at STP weighs 2 g, what is the molar mass of the gas?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;28.0 g · mol−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8.00 g · mol−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;56.0 g · mol−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;44.8 g · mol−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;179 g · mol−1 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real gases behave most nearly like ideal gases at&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;low temperatures and low pressures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;high temperatures and low pressures. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;high pressures and low molar masses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;high temperatures and high pressures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;low temperatures and high pressures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At high temperatures the gas molecules are moving more rapidly and the effects of the attractive forces are less significant. At low pressures the molecules are on average much further apart and the effects of the attractive forces are less significant because there are fewer ‘close encounters’.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculate the number of carbon atoms in 4.56 grams of ethanol (CH3CH2OH).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5.97 × 10^22&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5.49 × 10^24&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.19 × 10^23 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.53 × 10^26&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.79 × 10^23&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
m_CH3CH2OH = 4.56 g
Each CH3CH2OH molecule contains two carbon atoms. There are Avogadro’s number of ethanol molecules in one mole of ethanol. We need the molecular mass of ethanol so we can convert grams of ethanol to moles ethanol: Molecular mass of CH3CH2OH&lt;br /&gt;
= 2(12.01 g/mol) + 6(1.01 g/mol) + 1(16.00 g/mol)&lt;br /&gt;
= 46.08 g/mol&lt;br /&gt;
We can use this molecular mass to convert g ethanol to mol ethanol:&lt;br /&gt;
? mol ethanol = 4.56 g CH3CH2OH × 1 mol CH3CH2OH / 46.08 g CH3CH2OH&lt;br /&gt;
= 0.09896 mol CH3CH2OH&lt;br /&gt;
We can now use Avogadro’s number and the ratio of C atoms to CH3CH2OH molecules to find the number of carbon atoms:&lt;br /&gt;
? atoms C = 0.09896 mol CH3CH2OH&lt;br /&gt;
	× 6.022 × 10^23 molec CH3CH2OH / 1 mol CH3CH2OH&lt;br /&gt;
	× 2 atoms C / 1 molec CH3CH2OH&lt;br /&gt;
	= 1.192 × 1023 atoms C  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the reaction&lt;br /&gt;
2 NH3 + CH3OH → products ,&lt;br /&gt;
how much CH3OH is needed to react with 93.5 g of NH3?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;46.8 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.75 mol &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;5.50 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;11.3 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;88.1 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.31 mol&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;3.32 mol&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
mNH3 = 93.5g&lt;br /&gt;
? mol CH3OH = 93.5 g NH3 × 1 mol NH3 / 17 g NH3 × 1 mol CH3OH / 2 mol NH3&lt;br /&gt;
= 2.75 mol CH3OH  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the average speed of a carbon dioxide molecule is 410 m · s−1 at 25◦C, what is the average speed of a molecule of methane at the same temperature?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;679 m · s−1 &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;410 m · s−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;247 m · s−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1130 m · s−1&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1000 m · s−1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
From kinetic molecular theory, the temperature is directly proportional to mean KE.
KEmean= 1/2(MW)(average molecular speed)^2&lt;br /&gt;
and knowing T is constant,&lt;br /&gt;
…&lt;br /&gt;
v_CO2 = 679.08 m/s&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isoamyl acetate (C7H14O2) is a chemical compound that has a strong odor similar to bananas. At room temperature, the rms velocity of a isoamyl acetate molecule in the gas phase is approximately 240 m s^−1.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About how long will it take an isoamyl acetate molecule to diffuse 24 m across a room filled with air at SATP?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;About 0.1 second, since it is traveling 240 m s^−1.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The molecule will never diffuse across the room because it is too large.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Faster than 0.1 second, since 240 m s^−1 is the rms velocity which is not the same as the average velocity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Much longer than 0.1 second, because the molecule will have many collisions with other gas molecules. &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Because the isoamyl acetate will undergo many (too many too count) collisions it will take much much much longer than 0.1 second to diffuse 24 m. The answer could only be 0.1 seconds if the molecule had no collisions with other gas molecules. It is true that the rms velocity is not the average. It is also true that there is a distribution of velocities and some molecules will be moving faster. However, they will also undergo many many collisions causing them to take much more than 0.1 s to move 24 m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use van der Waals’ equation to calculate the pressure exerted by 1.25 mol of ammonia at −0.1◦C in a 1.54 L container. The van der Waals’ constants for ammonia are a = 4.00 L2·atm/mol2 and b = 0.0400 L/mol. (The values for a and b have been rounded off to simplify the arithmetic.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8.08102 atm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;32.3241 atm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;21.5494 atm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;16.162 atm &lt;strong&gt;correct&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;12.1215 atm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mixture of three gases, A, B, and C, is at a total pressure of 6.2 atm. The partial pressure of gas A is 1.63 atm; that of gas B is 3.78 atm. What is the partial pressure of gas C?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.43&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.24&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.09&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.4&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.91&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.79&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.97&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;0.85&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;2.59&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1.17&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correct answer: 0.79 atm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Explanation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
PT =6.2atm&lt;br /&gt;
PA =1.63atm&lt;br /&gt;
PB =3.78atm 
PC =?  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PT = PA + PB + PC&lt;br /&gt;
PC =PT −(PA+PB)&lt;br /&gt;
= 6.2 atm − (1.63 atm + 3.78 atm)&lt;br /&gt;
= 0.79 atm  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-1-exam/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://mathsci.co//chemistry/unit-1-exam/</guid>
        
        
        <category>chemistry</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
